hey aush students here's period 6 in
just 3
[Music]
minutes period 6 spans from 1865 to 1898
the Gilded Age saw the development of
Corporations like us steel and standard
oil these businesses were run by wealthy
industrial capitalists like Andrew
Carnegie and John de Rockefeller new
business practices like the formation of
trusts and vertical and horizontal
integration enable these companies to
form monopolies this was possible
because of a string of Republican
presidents who supported Le Fair
policies workers endured long hours low
p and poor conditions this led to the
rise of labor unions like the American
Federation of Labor who use strikes and
collective bargaining to fight for
change but strikes like the great
Railroad Strike and the Pullman Strike
were unsuccessful because the government
sided with businesses unions were also
blamed for Chicago's Hay Market Square
riot but during this time there were
some attempts to control businesses like
the Sherman Antitrust Act and the
Interstate Commerce Commission new
philosophies also emerged during the
guilded age for example social Darwinism
was the economic form of Darwin survival
of the fittest while Andrew Carnegie's
Gospel of wealth argued that it was the
duty of the wealthy to donate their
wealth to fund libraries schools and
Community projects also the social
gospel movement aimed to apply Christian
principles to the problems caused by
industrialization and urbanization this
period also saw the rise of immigration
and urbanization tenement houses were
built for the poor and for immigrants
who often settled in ethnic
neighborhoods while the antum period saw
immigration mostly from Germany and
Ireland these new immigrants mostly came
from Southern and Eastern Europe and
political machines like Tam Hall often
took advantage of these immigrants by
trading service for votes nativism also
increased especially against Chinese
immigrants who arrived on the west coast
which led to the passage of the Chinese
Exclusion Act As Americans moved West
under the Homestead Act corporations
also looked West the Transcontinental
Railroad was finally completed in 1869
connecting the East and West coasts and
railroads expanded across the west
through government land grants Mining
and ranching were also set up in western
territories but the rapid development of
the West had devastating consequences
for Native Americans who inhabited these
lands and led to the decimation of buff
populations intentions exploded in the
plains Wars which dominated the late
1800s tribes like the nesp and the
Lakota Su fought to maintain their
ancestral lands and their autonomy but
the US Army devastated these tribes at
tragic events like the S Creek Massacre
and it wounded me despite the efforts of
indigenous peoples like the Ghost Dance
Movement or their victory at Little Big
Horn these tribes were ultimately
defeated and the Decades of government
injustices against Native Americans was
exposed in Helen Hunt Jackson's book A
Century of Dishonor meanwhile
assimilationist schools like the
infamous Carlile School sought to erase
native culture and force conversion to
Christianity and the 1887 Daw severalty
act broke up tribal lands offering
citizenship to natives who agreed to
assimilate industry also expanded in the
South Atlanta journalist Henry Grady
promoted what he called a new South a
South that was focused on economic
diversity Southern cities like
Birmingham and Memphis built steel mills
and lumber plants while Georgia and the
Carolinas built textile factories and
Virginia established tobacco
manufacturing plants and finally period
6 saw the rise of the populist movement
populist from mostly farmers who
struggled with low crop prices and debt
their Omaha platform supported the
unlimited coinage of silver a graduated
income tax and the direct election of
senators their platform was adopted by
Democrat candidate William Jennings
Bryan in the election of 1896 where he
gave the famous Cross of gold speech
supporting B metalism but he lost to
Republican candidate William McKinley
thanks for watching and if you want more
aush helps like study guides timelines
and summary videos make sure you check
out the ultimate review packet